不可变类型。
Immutable types.
如果你在数据型超市购物
If you were shopping in a data type supermarket
你必须在一个无聊的不可变字符串之间做出选择
and you had to choose between a boring immutable string
一个真正有权势的人
and a really powerful do anything
可变字符串生成器，为什么在地球上
mutable string builder, why on Earth
你会选择不变的那个吗？
would you choose the immutable one?
字符串生成器应该能够执行所有操作
String builder should be able to do everything
毕竟它的弦可以做，
that its string can do, after all,
伴随着这些突变，比如设置和附加
along with these mutations, like setting and appending
删除其他所有内容。
and delete and everything else.
答案是不可变的类型
And the answer is immutable types actually
更好地满足本课程的三个原则。
satisfy much better the three principles of this course.
它们对虫子更安全。
They're safer from bugs.
它们更容易理解。
They're easier to understand.
他们更愿意改变。
And they're more ready for change.
易变性使它更难理解
Mutability makes it harder to understand
你的程序在做什么而且更难
what your program is doing and much harder
执行合同。
to enforce contracts.
我们将举几个例子
And we're going to have a few examples in this reading that
说明原因。
illustrate why.
第一个例子说明了什么会出错
First example shows what can go wrong
当您将可变值传递给方法时。
when you're passing a mutable value into a method.
所以让我们从一个简单的方法开始
So let's start with a simple method that
将列表中的整数相加。
sums up the integers in a list.
所以这里需要一个列表。
So it takes a list here.
它在列表的值上循环，
It loops over the values of that list,
x取列表中出现的所有整数，
x takes on every integer that appears in that list,
我们只是把它们加在一起。
and we're simply adding them to this sum.
然后我们还这笔钱。
And then we return that sum.
这就是它的合同承诺的，
And that's what its contract promises,
它会把钱还回来
that it's going to return the sum
名单上的号码。
of the numbers in this list.
很简单。
Simple enough.
假设现在我们还需要一个方法
Suppose now we also need a method
对列表中数字的绝对值求和。
that sums the absolute values of the numbers in the list.
现在，也许我们的程序员想跟随
Now, maybe our programmer wants to follow
很好，不要重复练习。
good don't repeat yourself practice.
记住，我们说过不要重复
Remember, we talked about don't repeat yourself
在先前的阅读中。
in an earlier reading.
所以他们写了一个方法，使用sum作为子例程。
And so they write a method that uses sum as a sub routine.
所以绝对值之和是假设的
So sum of absolute values is supposed
返回绝对值之和
to return the sum of the absolute values
在名单上的数字里。
in the numbers in the list.
所以拿着那张单子
So takes that list of numbers and it's
应该给出绝对值的和。
supposed to give the sum of the absolute values.
让我们继续使用sum，换句话说，
And let's go ahead and reuse sum, in other words,
构造此实现，以便我们可以简单地调用sum。
structure this implementation so we can simply call sum.
程序的运行方式
And the way the program is going to do
就在他们要循环的时候
that is while they're going to loop
通过此列表中每个元素的索引
through the indexes of each of the elements in this list
更改列表的值。
and change the value of the list.
因此，将索引I处的元素替换为其绝对值。
So replace the element at index I with its absolute value.
然后我们可以简单地调用结果列表上的sum。
And then we can simply call sum on that resulting list.
所以这个方法通过直接改变列表来完成它的工作。
So this method does its job by mutating the list directly.
对程序员来说似乎很明智
Seems sensible actually to a programmer
因为重用现有列表非常有效。
because it's very efficient to reuse this existing list.
如果清单上有几百万个项目，
If the list happens to be millions of items long,
那么你就节省了时间和记忆
then you're saving the time and memory
生成新的百万项绝对值列表
of generating a new million item list of the absolute values
在你叫苏姆之前。
before you call sum.
所以实现者有两个很好的理由
So the implementer has two very good reasons
对于这种设计，不要重复，
for this kind of design, don't repeat yourself,
他们在这里重用这些代码和性能。
they're reusing this code here, and performance.
但最终的结果是
But the resulting behavior is going
对任何一个
to be very surprising to any client who
尝试使用此函数。
tries to use this function.
例如，假设我们在某个地方有一个主方法
For example, imagine that we have a main method some place
上面有一个数字列表。
that has a list of numbers.
它想打印出绝对值
And it wants to print the absolute values
以及打印总数
of those numbers as well as printing the sum
这些数字中的一个。
of those numbers just as is.
问题是，这个代码会打印什么？
The question is, what will this code print?
会打印5加3加2等于10吗
Will it print 5 plus 3 plus 2 is 10
然后负5加负3加负2
and then negative 5 plus negative 3 plus negative 2
是负10，还是会有其他作用？
is negative 10, or will it do something else?